<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Development on Raen </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://dpraen.github.io/raen/categories/development/index.xml</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <updated>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>misunderstanding static vs dynamic</title>
      <link>https://dpraen.github.io/raen/post/static-vs-dynamic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2017 10:56:07 SAST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dpraen.github.io/raen/post/static-vs-dynamic/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;static&#34;&gt;Static&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dynamic&#34;&gt;Dynamic&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>microsoft&#39;s coding ai</title>
      <link>https://dpraen.github.io/raen/post/microsoft-coding-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 10:56:07 SAST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dpraen.github.io/raen/post/microsoft-coding-ai/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn1.tnwcdn.com/wp-content/blogs.dir/1/files/2016/11/14-nov-blog-2-796x398.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://thenextweb.com/artificial-intelligence/2017/02/23/microsofts-new-ai-sucks-at-coding-as-much-as-the-typical-stack-overflow-user/#.tnw_V6JxUG6q&#34;&gt;Microsoft has released a new artificial intelligence that can write code.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;automation-hysteria&#34;&gt;automation hysteria&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people in the tech community have been reacting badly to this. I&amp;rsquo;m not even a bit concerned, and in fact, think that if tools like this are perfected, it would be a great boon for developers. I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-coding-ai&#34;&gt;a coding ai&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, what this thing does is use a database of code snippets, and combines them into something usable. As in the linked article, this can be said to be similar to a typical &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stackoverflow.com&#34;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; user, who copies and pastes code from the site and then modifies it to do what he or she needs. The &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo; part is how the AI determines which code fragments are suitable, and fits them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-it-shouldn-t-concern-the-average-developer&#34;&gt;why it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t concern the average developer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development isn&amp;rsquo;t all about writing code - it&amp;rsquo;s about determining what the problem is, and then writing out a logical solution to that problem, usually in the form of code. This AI won&amp;rsquo;t be able to determine a problem or write specifications by itself, so it will still be humans who need to do that. In order for a machine to determine problems and find logical solutions, a much broader AI will need to be developed - one that can build its own metal model of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-this-will-actually-help-developers&#34;&gt;why this will actually help developers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment this tool can only handle problems that can be solved with around 5 lines of code. A promising start, but a lot of work needs to be done. Let&amp;rsquo;s say that this is perfected - the tool will help developers rather than replace them. Think of it as another layer of abstraction. Just another step in a long tradition, from the first compiler to fourth generation high level languages. Thinking that a non-developer could be as skillful at using this new AI tool as an experienced developer is probably disingenuous. It may make programming more accessible, but the most productive developers will still be &amp;hellip; well, developers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
